I don't call it over. The regular skin to mean my city council from Monday, December 2nd, 2024.
Two book and put us get the personal passes. We have none. Three claims list.
Let's do proof.
Sorry.
All right.
Double gold.
Joe.
Aye.
Four minutes from October 28th.
And November 4th.
Regular skin to means.
Motion to print.
Second.
Double gold.
Aye.
Five.
We need to crash the center.
Outside organization update and discussion.
Let's kill.
My name is Kelsey. I'm the executive director of the Community Crisis Center.
And if you're not familiar with this, we serve those impacted by domestic violence, sexual assault and stalking.
We're actually a regional agency.
We provide services in Ottawa, Delaware, and Craig.
But we're headquartered here in Ottawa County.
So here in Miami, we have a 24-bed shelter.
Two transitional.
Two bedroom apartments.
And then our main office.
Which serves all clients from Ottawa County.
And an exciting update.
We had the Oklahoma Attorney General office come out today.
And they're going to come back in January.
But we are really close to getting our human trafficking certification.
There's only three providers in the entire state that are certified.
None of them are rural.
And there's not been a new agency come on in 10 years.
So we're really excited about that.
We served seven individuals that were victims of human sex or labor trafficking this past year.
So we're seeing a really big need in the community and excited to provide that service.
You guys give us a $25,000 utility waiver for our shelter.
Which we are extremely appreciative of.
Last year we were the highest serving rural shelter in the entire state of Oklahoma for domestic violence victims.
We house 219 individuals and 83 of those were children.
So that waiver goes a long way in helping us pay our bills.
Which is you guys can imagine what household costs are.
You multiply that by 219 people.
Food insurance utilities.
It's pretty high.
Our services are very broad.
And I'd be happy to answer any questions you guys have.
That we provide advocacy court services, counseling, legal,
support one families are leaving the shelter.
Is there anything specific you guys want to know?
I already knows you guys provide me in a year's time.
Typically over 25,000.
Serve a lot of food.
And then what's the head count that comes through your facility on a yearly basis?
It depends for shelter specifically.
We house about 220 to 250.
Last year we served 933 individuals between our 3 counties.
We serve more people non-residentially.
Which means they come into an office.
They get court services, advocacy, then we do in shelter.
The shelter is obviously a one.
our average days about 53 days.
There is a state report that comes out by the Attorney General's Office.
It's called the Domestic Violence Facility Review Report.
Last year, Oklahoma was number two in the nation for women that were murdered by man they know.
And Ottawa County was three times the state average for domestic violence-related homicides.
So we're seeing a really big need in the community, and our numbers seem to be increasing every year.
Do you guys allow pets in your, in your crisis center?
We do not have an onsite kennel. It's a goal of ours, but we do, we're able to house support animals.
And then we have an outside kennel and a few pop up kennels.
But we partner with something called the Red Rover Grant.
So we're actually able to pay to board animals through that grant.
So we'll take someone immediately when they come in, just so they don't have to worry about pets when they're leaving.
And then we'll get them signed up for that program, and we use different facilities and down and they're able to board them while they're staying with us.
So that was a weird question asking.
But I recently learned that 48% of people won't leave the situation because of their dog or a cat or whatever.
They don't want to leave the animal there.
So it's important that they provide that kind of service.
So it's one less thing for the person to worry about when leaving a domestic violence situation.
Sorry, I've asked it on purpose.
Do you guys have any other questions?
Is there anything else we can do as a city to assist you?
Yes, actually.
We've been wanting to talk to you guys.
I don't know if it's even possible, but at the shelter we're on a lift station.
And with the amount of people that we have that are house there, it's really difficult because we're having to repair it very frequently.
What we were told when we came on is the reason that we had to have the lift station was because they were using the railroad tracks behind the facility which they're not anymore.
So I'm not sure if there's a possibility of running sewer to us because we spend thousands of dollars.
Every few years we're preparing that just the amount of people that come through.
So if that's a possibility, we'd like to chat more about that.
We'll have to look into it.
I'm assuming that being a NSF as we know, we're kind of protective of that railroad tracks, still.
I mean, it has the immense kind of test.
So I mean, it's just something I don't have to look at.
I'm assuming it's like you said because they grab the issues and that's why they're on a forcement.
And maybe we can see why you have so much issues with your forcement.
And maybe we help you guys with someone to get a bigger forcement or something.
You know, so many repairs.
Yeah, we would love that.
And other than that, I think just making sure that city employees are aware of our services.
I think one thing that we learned this last year, we did a community-wide need assessment.
And a majority of people that came to our services came because someone told them about us.
So it wasn't brochures or them finding it.
But it was someone that was a neighbor, a coworker, someone from church.
But somebody said, hey, I care about you.
I want you to be safe.
There's people that can help.
So that's just really important to us beyond anything else that people know that we're here.
That our services are 24 cents.
and we're one of the few services that are truly providing services every hour of every day.
We're never not providing a service with the shelter.
So we can take people middle the night to a weekend after hours whenever they need.
We're always here.
And you need to be in your new building.
So they've been over to your old building.
That's part of the heater twice.
I appreciate it.
We have been in a hundred-year-old two-story house.
And many of you, I said, probably seeing on B Street next to the child advocacy center,
the black and white building that's gone up.
That's our new office.
We're doubling our square footage.
We're really on a growth plan because of the amount of clients that we're serving.
And then adding the human trafficking services.
But the Attorney General's office was out today.
So we have to be certified underneath them.
That just says that our services are safe and accessible.
And all the things they have to be legally.
And they approved it.
So we're good to start moving in tomorrow.
All right.
All of you?
Yes.
Look at I know.
Shay wasn't moving because she couldn't yet.
Yep.
None of us have moved yet.
And they've given us the OK.
So we can officially transition our services.
Cool.
But if you guys have any employees that have down time,
we have a lot of furniture to put together.
Brian has been out helping.
So if you guys want to send anyone our way this week,
we would appreciate it.
I thank you all.
You all used.
No good to move.
Yep.
Some other.
No good came out.
And they helped with the P things.
Puring us come out.
And we've had a few individuals.
But we were able to regrant to purchase all new things for a new building,
which is really exciting.
But it's lots of things put together.
So we're still needing some help this week.
We appreciate everything you do.
Thank you, guys.
We've got a great team.
Well, thank you.
Thanks for having us.
And for the grant.
Thanks.
Thank you.
For this.
The community crisis scenario will be the first of some more outside organizations
that will have come present.
As much as you see.
And you know.
Start.
So.
Thank you.
Six annual sales commission agreement was.
Minota community facilities authority.
This is kind of a housekeeping matter.
This is the third year that the city has had an agreement with MCFA.
And what it does is it allows us to.
So advertising for the MCFA and get a commission.
Such as school board panels.
Banners advertising on the school board.
And then sweets.
School, minor public schools.
And any.
Also has the same agreement with MCFA.
So we're just improving the agreement.
Yes.
All right.
I'll make a motion.
Mr. Scott.
Thank you.
Doug Goldstein.
James?
Hi.
7.
Part 2 of a 2020-23 Dodger AM Truck for the Mercy Equipment Update from Superior
Auto Group and Award-Lisa Greenment to thank the Grand Lakes for Q24-0, 1 or 101,
2021-23 Dodger AM 1500, halftone truck crew cab.
Police vehicle with the Mercy Equipment Update.
In Council, we received bids to purchase the vehicle from Bob Howard Dodge, John Vance Motors,
and Superior Auto Group.
I just found out that Vance Motors went on ahead and sold the two ramps that they
had the trucks, so this is really between Bob Howard and Superior right now.
And Bob Howard came in at 41-29-9, we couldn't get them to quote the upfit we're still waiting
and then I wanted to have you see Superior came in at 37-480, and they had a $10,000 roughly
$500 upfit charge.
Vance came in at 23,994 for an upfit charge, which would have put them up 60,000 plus.
So we feel like the last year's model, although it's new, was a really good deal.
And I guess this is the last night that Superior is going to hold those two.
You can't find these 23's at Martin Prices, like you could, a while back.
So anyway, we want to go with Superior Auto Group.
This is for the police department.
And the banks, we didn't get a bit from security, well, it came in at 4.98, our vest at 5.15,
our national 4-8-1, and Bank of Britain like 4-6-7.
And we recommend purchasing the Dodger Amtruck with the upfit from Superior Auto Group, and we
need your approval.
Todd, are these tracks going on patrol?
Can you talk in you address, like, you know, you told me about how we can't get certain vehicles
now?
Yeah, so who would just go on your bed and leave?
There are only options for air sectors, and this is just not only for money, but are those
your only two models that you're looking at?
As you have the city doesn't talk about it.
Right.
That's not a city that doesn't talk about it.
The air conditioners in the Dering Hill are, they're not milk, like they should be.
That's important.
That's like a trust man.
Well, you consider when we just sent one to the shop to the air conditioner, and it was almost
$8,000.
Well, right now, if you buy any vehicle for $48,000, if I buy it on a bike, there's no
one else you can buy one for there right now.
Todd, do you have any concern with like maneuverability of a truck versus like a small
SUV or mid-sized SUV?
Yeah.
The service, you know, the beer's in the road, I mean, it can clear, you know, have anything inside
their vehicle or just anything messy that nobody else wants to touch that we pass the
place that can't go in the bed of a truck, and it's really empty, but it's empty, and
then it's empty.
And then yeah.
So these fold up.
Four cages or half cages.
I'll make a motion to prove.
Cool.
Hi.
Just that?
Parker.
Eight.
Part of the 2020-23 Dodge Ram Truck with the Mercy Equipment Eplist from Screar.
Auto group and award lease purchase agreement to group bank grant rate Q24 dash zero one zero two
223 dot ram fifteen hundred have done
truck crew cab please vehicle with mercy equipment up there so the same thing just this one is the same except this one came in at forty-four dollars higher approximately and
It was just a touch different on the trim level
right a different on the price motion to approve
second
done goal
I
James I
Park
five discussion possible action center court logo design
the new Civic Center gym floor
All right, why do you guys know that we are getting a new
Do you explore a mistakes in there, and what I've done actually just internally is through
together some logos.
We'll have a serious court, and bring them to you guys to approve one of them, fire all
of them, tell them to go back to the drum board, or whatever.
So, I'll kind of open five different options, and basically, you've got option A, B, and
C, D, and E, and E, we'll go through them real quick.
Option A is your regular signal, option B is a little bit of an option B, so I'm going to
go up here, but similar, but take the bottom out, and then add a certain center, and then
we've got a certain center.
And the last two options is, basically, the sports and right logo.
So, it looks like I just do this together with my computer, my office, don't use together,
but thought it'd be good to bring these up to you guys to see.
Can you move it to C and D?
Yeah, and I'm here.
Let's just see how this is obviously your center board.
Sorry.
That's okay.
That's what I'm going to do, that's what I'm going to do.
You have to have those black lines on there?
That's not even a little co-option.
That's what the board looks like.
You have to sort of pull up a circle.
So, those will be in there, but there won't be that, like you see, going over the logo, you'll actually
come around and stop and start that like this.
There's the trigger.
There's just a little bit there.
There's two, and then you set it on the top.
There's a little bit there.
And the logo that we put in for the B will be 12.
Can the lines be blue instead of black?
Um, but in there, but in which black lines were the actual.
We got, we got some time.
We got two weeks, three weeks, maybe a month.
Actually, you started with this.
I don't think we'll see anything happens in the form to a product, of course.
Where is some action to change the city's logo?
Isn't that a quick, I mean, that would mean.
It is the city logo.
Yeah, I think that would be correct, but the current.
And you don't have to do anything to change that?
No, we're talking about it.
Well, you know, we had talked about it.
We talked about it, whatever.
I mean, it's probably something we would have to budget for next year to pay a firm or what.
We would have to say to put this logo on it in the last year.
Right.
Can there's some back later?
And be down with anyone, and not do this right now?
Yeah, so I'm going to install a port now.
I mean, basically I come back in, saying it all down to the bare wood.
Install a logo.
I'll come back.
I'll be the way if you put the logo on.
You don't want to change.
I'm going to have something out there.
We'd have to go with A right now, right?
No.
I thought we had to.
Oh, so the change in the logo is a separate issue in this.
Yeah.
Yeah, separate issue.
So if it's that something else besides what our logo says, underneath it.
Oh, I thought that.
I'll talk to your snakes.
Some snakes.
They don't, they don't.
Yeah.
Is that a previous name?
Do you guess he's off now?
Are you wearing it in the City of Logan?
Yep.
I understand now.
But that would probably be something we would budget for.
Is there any way to maybe get rid of all the words and just do the end or something in the middle of that circle or
Yeah, I just I just it seems a little worry and just kind of
What and I know you just kind of the lines and stuff for yeah, but I just think that just the block
Yeah, something because it it just kind of seems
Right
It's the Mac
And now you know why I kicked him off my butt
So could you guys maybe bring this back with maybe some options of just the M
Yeah, or something
It's a go back and change
That was when I was gravitating towards yeah, you did that him so if we did be
It's really not gonna be that big deal to go back and change because you're gonna send out the spot anyway for the new
If we don't do anything right now, we're still gonna have to go and say it's the same cross
Well, I mean, I'm not just saying just that I honestly I'm not just crazy about
Any of them of them. I look option B would be my pick. I'm just not
Obsessed with any of them at this point which is why I suggest you maybe
Come back with
So what kind of time for you guys on to have a decision on this we're offering you to bear the next
So you're wanting to approach something next meeting?
On the floor, on the floor, on the floor itself.
We still have time on the low ground.
Yeah.
If they're going to have to floor and put it low, go back.
So we still, we can bring you something back.
Okay.
Yeah.
You're going to keep moving.
You're also going to have the process of actually getting more and more.
Okay.
We can bring both of them.
Those guys want to.
Need?
Okay.
Perfect.
Go back to the drawing board.
I think suggestions you have, you see those?
Yeah.
We have a good time.
And I'll point it back in.
10.
Mayor's nomination to reappoint the ceremony.
To the mile of CVB.
Turn to expire 11.
21 of 27.
Motion to approve.
Are you a step?
Hi.
11.
Mayor's nomination to reappoint Gary Crow to the mile of CVB.
Turn to expire 11.
21.
27.
Motion to approve.
Second.
Hello.
Hi.
I'm 12.
Other than the business of any of which is posted on the agenda.
13 staff reports.
I'm here to point out a couple of things on there.
So we have the sales tax community comparison.
And then we also have the PCAX collection.
So I'm as everyone knows, you know,
G.R.D.A. recently raised our race.
Our city analysis.
They're going through.
They've kind of came up some different ideas.
And we're kind of going back and forth with them.
I would think maybe our rating increase may be contingent upon, you know,
a slight rating increase.
And then once the PCAX falls off,
and we would, you know, do the second part or whatever.
Kind of less than the blow.
But so we have about that shows.
We've updated today to about five months.
So I think this shows.
Yeah, 5.29.
So about four and a half to five months till it would be paid off.
We should be good.
So again.
Sorry.
So we updated today on the.
It'll be, it's about four and a half months until it's paid off.
I'm on the sheet of this 5.29.
But we updated it since we put the packet together.
So.
Good.
Because you know, every week we have, you know, a cycle coming in.
Did you understand what I was saying though?
Like on a rating increase.
We may try to do a small rating increase.
And then like do a two part increase or something.
You know, before so we can.
Less than the blow.
the citizens and so if we do that, this just makes sure we explain that very well too.
Yeah.
It was just an idea.
I agree with you, but we're explaining to them why we're doing that, we have less than
a blow and that way people understand exactly what we're doing because I know they're probably
waiting for this roll off, but you're right unless the blow, because you're not used to this,
but we need to make sure they're aware of what we're doing and I like to ask all the
reason they're up there at their rate, so we're not having to compare some of the different
cities that are raising because of the rating creeps, so because you know as long as I do,
they're going to say, say, you can't rely on them, but you just say, it's going to what's happening.
Well, we need to get through it.
And it's going to understand them, but there's something to do with the comparison, so I don't know the
website too.
Yeah, that's what I'm saying.
But in my comparison together right now, it's always present.
To me, I mean, it's hard for everyone to say, okay, south all is the same as us, and they're
rates are this, and here's our rates.
So 14 Mayor, Council from the Indian Council, I like to just say, I appreciate all the effort that's
going on downtown with Christmas and all the businesses that are participating, it seems like
it's bigger and better every year, and I know you drive some of that, so I appreciate your
efforts too.
I know you do too, but I was, I'm sorry, but I'm looking at that, but I'm not talking about that.
Now, because you're down there in it all the time, and then you've done a fantastic job with your
shorts.
I saw it for the first time.
Thank you.
Last week, when I was going to the gym, because it was dark out in the end of the thing happened.
So what these are today, one of the first balls went up today.
Oh, really?
Yeah.
Green ones up and the blue ones up.
Like the bank are elected for that.
Okay, that's one out there.
I'm going to go and pull me on.
I think it's cool that a few years ago, we met a commitment to better our downtown Christmas and
we're seeing the effects of it, and it's really neat.
Well, I'm working together, and I also thank you too, but this has really been an advocate for
shopping locally.
I think business in Miami, and bringing new business to Miami, I also thank you, but yeah, I do appreciate
your effort in doing your lives downtown and doing future businesses.
I don't think there's probably any other mayors in the world that are doing that.
So.
the Coleman, I don't know if any of you guys did, it was a great time, family loved it.
So I'll make sure you guys are kind of just looking out for different events that they're
doing because it was really fun and I liked it.
I'm really happy to be here.
This whole week, it seems like my gosh.
This whole month, I feel like it's just kind of impact with a lot of guys.
I wish I had been able to count on her with it right now.
Actually, I actually pulled it down.
Did you hear her say something?
Yeah.
So Christmas parade is Saturday, tree lighting is Friday, all the home tour is Sunday.
So the packed weekend this weekend, it's stuff to do.
But thank you to all of our crews.
I don't want to leave anybody out.
It's a crew effort and team effort.
I see people from all different departments downtown decorating and decorating a tree and hanging lights.
Everybody is on board.
And I greatly appreciate it.
I've been getting tons of messages from people saying they love downtown.
They love driving through and seeing a lit up at night.
The Christmas spirit, the people get translate to our small businesses.
And of course, that translates to us and our sales tax revenue,
where we get to do more things for the people that have just been there dollars here.
So that's all driven by city staff.
So greatly appreciate everything everybody does.
I know we get credit sometimes for your work.
But without you guys, our jobs will be a lot more difficult.
So thank you for all you guys do.
It doesn't go on notice by us.
We know what you guys are known and we greatly appreciate that.
So keep up the good work.
It is noticed.
And the community spirit is getting there.
It's taken us a while to get it there.
But every people are starting to get on board.
And they're starting to see the effects of now.
The tree and there's people going crazy about the tree.
But we're going to keep getting the tree because it's cool deal.
And I even had people from other areas messaging me saying they wish they had.
But tree like ours and decorations like ours.
So you're always going to have those that are never happy with anything.
The cave people.
So we're always going to have those.
But appreciate everything you guys are doing.
15 city manager communication.
I'm just about what their mayor said.
You know, Linda's been working hard.
So we actually have a post for Christmas for the week.
And so we have all the items that go on this week.
Which is really cool with their different times.
So I know we get asked as the board and as the city manager.
Like what time is this?
What time is this?
So you can look on our Facebook page.
I mean, I mean, I don't know if I'm going to tree line to holiday home too or so.
presentation, so we have all that. The second thing is, I know we have previously talked to the board
about we have the two buildings that we own downtown, the whole folks building in the Buffalo Sun,
toward down before the parade. Just for clarity, that's the old mark folks building, not the old folks?
Yes. Thank you. Dr. Ford. Thank you. So we've actually recently had some interest.
Do you know I have an retirement home downtown?
Thank you, Brian. You're welcome. So we recently had some interest in those buildings to purchase
as the buildings has. So I've just asked what you were interested to submit to us
an offer and writing and then we present the board. I said, you know, those different idea
than what we came up with, but I mean, we're listening to anything. So that's what we haven't started
because I don't want to have a building halfway, right? We couldn't use that.
So the last folks on the net is the kind of updated everybody on the fiber. So we've reached out to four different
fiber companies that do this all over the world. We've had some really good conversations with them. They've asked us
to do a poll inventory so they can do a better, get us a more cost effective price for the design.
So we're actually in the process of doing a poll inventory, I'm sure you can talk to them
later about today at lunch. This way we can get a better design cost for the design. So once we do that, then
we, once we have that done, which would be around the first of this year, then we'll put it out for a bit for the
design. So kind of, we talked to a vendor last week and he said, every utility that has, so like a
electric utility that's done this, that they've been a part of it been very successful because they have those
polls. They have a lot of the things that they're successful. So our thought would be we would, you know,
the people were a lot of first year to kind of get the community engaged. On our utility float, Derek is actually going to
have something to kind of get people the excitement stirred up. He has a picture on his phone if you'd like to look at it.
It's kind of a play on home alone. He's your little teaser for it. So they kind of get the excitement for the project and everything.
So are you going to dress up this little thing, guys?
I don't know what you're going to do.
Do you still stand by?
No.
What are you going to do tonight when you got when you see him wearing those?
I'm going to be so mad.
I know you got them.
She's going to ask me to handcuff things to have a teaser.
I'll think of that.
That would be good. Maybe get some stuff clear up and kind up on everything.
I'm going to try the ones that aren't in need of that.
Especially for them.
Was it killed?
Right.
Like it.
16 a.m.
most to adjourn.
Take care.
Bye.
Dr. Cole.
Right.
Dr. Farns.
Hi.
Parker.
Bye.